- Hola, soy Amanda.
- Hola, soy Elizabeth.
- Hola, soy Alexis.
- Hi, soy Mufa.
- Bienvenidos.
- A otro.
- Episodio.
- Episodio de.
- Clean code.
- Vamos a emprender un viaje.
- Para emprender un viaje de ...
- En este episodio.
- Episodio.
- Wuujuu!.
- Por Uncle Bob.
- Uncle Bob.
- Disfruten!
- Bienvenidos, bienvenidos a la nueva versión
del episodio uno de Clean Code.
Permíteme tomar tu sombrero.
Entonces, han pasado dos años y medio
desde que escribí y produje
ese primer episodio.
Y ahora con 20 episodios en nuestro haber,
pensamos que era hora de
resaltar ese viejo primer episodio
y llevarlo a nuestros
estándares actuales de
scripting, video, y edición de audio.
After all, this is the first
episode that many people
are going to see, and we think that
first impressions are important,
so we refactored the whole thing.
And so, without further ado,
here is the newer, cleaner
episode one, Clean Code.
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
In 1908, Henrietta Swan
Leavitt, an Astronomer working
at Harvard, made an incredible discovery,
one that would change astronomy forever.
Astrophotography was just
coming into its heyday.
Astronomers were producing
so many photographic plates
that they didn't have
time to analyze them all.
Back then, women were not
allowed to operate the
telescopes, but they were
deemed capable of making
measurements on photographic plates
and doing calculations
based on those measurements.
Leavitt, who initially worked for no pay
and was later paid 30 cents an hour,
was asked by her boss, Edward Pickering,
to study and measure variable stars,
stars that change their
brightness over time.
Finding and studying variable stars using
photographic plates is not an easy task.
You begin with one photographic plate
that has hundreds and
hundreds of stars on it,
and then you measure each
individual star's brightness
by measuring the diameter of the spot
on the photographic plate.
And you do this for
every star on the plate.
And then you get another
photographic plate
from the same part of the sky
taken at a different time,
and you do all those measurements again,
and you correlate them, looking for stars
that changed in brightness.
And then you do that
again and again and again
for hundreds and hundreds of plates
over years and years.
In Leavitt's case, it was the 20 years
between 1893 and 1912.
And in those fateful decades,
she made one of the most
amazingly useful discoveries
in the history of astronomy.
You see, she noticed something peculiar
about the magellanic clouds.
Now these clouds, to
the naked eye, are just
patches of fuzz on the
Southern hemisphere sky,
but on a photographic plate
taken through a telescope,
they are clouds of millions
upon millions of stars.
What Leavitt noticed was
that thousands of those stars
in the magellanic clouds
were variable stars,
their brightness changed over time.
Now there's a certain
kind of variable star
called a cepheid variable.
And cepheid variables pulsate
with very regular rhythms.
Some of them pulsate
once in a couple of days,
others will pulsate once
in a couple of weeks.
Why they pulsate will be a
topic of another episode.
Leavitt found many such cepheid variables
in the magellanic clouds,
all pulsating at different rates.
But then she noticed something
that wasn't true elsewhere.
The brighter cepheid variables
in the magellanic clouds
pulsated more slowly than the dimmer ones.
Why would this be true
of the magellanic clouds
but not elsewhere in the sky?
But then it occurred to her.
What if all the stars
in the magellanic cloud
were roughly the same distance from us?
If that was true, then
the rate at which the
cepheid variables pulsated was related
to their actual brightness.
She did the math and came up
with a simple and beautiful
formula called the period
luminosity relationship.
Given the period of a star
in the magellanic clouds,
using this formula, she
could predict luminosity,
or given the luminosity of a
star in the magellanic clouds,
she could use the formula
to predict the period.
Now, maybe you're wondering
why this was so useful,
but let me tell you, it's really useful.
And the reason is that if
you can measure the distance
to just one cepheid variable
star, one that's nearby,
then you can calibrate
Leavitt's formula to tell you
where any cepheid variable star is.
So long as you can measure
its period and luminosity,
you can calculate its distance.
Needless to say, the hunt was on.
And it was just a year
later that Ejnar Hertzsprung
measured the distance to
several cepheid variable stars.
Using those numbers, Leavitt's
formula was calibrated
such that it could tell
you the distance to any
cepheid variable if you could measure its
period and its average luminosity.
Let me repeat that.
We could now accurately
determine the distance
to any object that contained
a cepheid variable.
What objects contain cepheid variables?
Oh, globular clusters, galaxies,
but that's a topic for another day.
For now, just remember that
the measuring stick we use
to measure the universe
itself was the result of
the careful and dedicated
efforts of one remarkable woman,
Henrietta Swan Leavitt.
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
In 2008, Kent Beck wrote
this wonderful book,
Implementation Patterns.
It's full of tips and techniques
that programmers can use
to keep their code nicely
structured and well ordered.
But he began this book
with what I consider
to be a striking statement.
He said, "Actually, this
book is built on a rather
"fragile premise that good code matters."
- Fragile? Fragile?
I don't see anything fragile
about the fact that good code matters,
of course it matters!
What nonsense to think otherwise.
Hmph!
- Of course, as the author
of this book, Clean Code,
I have to agree, clean code matters a lot.
- Indeed, clean code
can make the difference
between the ultimate success or failure
of your company.
- I've experienced this quite directly.
Here, let me tell you this story of
the company killed by code.
In 1988, or thereabouts, I
was working for a company.
And we were building a large
network management system in C.
We purchased a debugger
from a company named Sword.
It allowed us to single
step and breakpoint
our way through our C code.
- Whoa, like, you know
I've got to debug my
Ruby source code all the time, you know.
- Yeah, but back then a
source-level debugger was a rarity.
I mean most of the time
we debugged in hex.
- (laughing) Yeah,
(laughing) yeah, yeah,
that sounds like a nightmare.
(laughing)
- Oh, it was.
Of course, it's all we knew, but it was.
But look, this Sword tool was great.
I mean it was very
powerful, and it saved us
a boatload of time and effort.
We loved it.
- Gosh, Uncle Bob,
that must've been a really
popular product back then.
- Oh, it was.
I mean they were doing a gang
buster business at first.
The trade journals loved them,
and the folks at user
groups and conferences,
they couldn't get enough.
A couple of years later, it was 1990,
and we started dreaming about switching
from C to C++.
We called Sword and asked
them whether they'd be
supporting C++ anytime soon.
They told us that the C++ version would be
coming pretty soon.
But time wore on.
For six months it wore on.
But finally, the C++ version
of the Sword debugger arrived.
(party horn) We were really excited.
And so we installed it and we fired it up.
But it took 45 minutes to
load and then it crashed.
- (laughing) Yeah.
(laughing) Boom.
(laughing)
- Well, we didn't think it was so funny.
Debugging C++ in hex is
not an awful lot of fun,
so we called up Sword
and we told them they had
to fix this problem, and they swore to us
that they'd fix it in the next release.
- (laughing) Yeah.
(laughing) And I bet it took
'em another six months (laughs)
to send you a new release. (laughing)
Yes, Jerry, it did, and believe me,
our patience was growing mighty thin.
- (laughing) Yeah, yeah.
And then when you got it, (laughing)
it still took 45 minutes to load
and then it crashed, didn't it? (laughing)
- Yes, Jerry, that's
exactly what happened.
Needless to say, we cancelled our license
and got on about our business.
From our point of view,
that product was dead.
(beeping sounds)
- [Broadcaster] We interrupt this program
to bring you a special news bulletin.
Sword Inc., famed creator of
the very popular C debugger
has declared bankruptcy and
closed its doors forever.
We now return you to your
regularly scheduled program.
- Yeah, it was just a few
months after that disastrous
second release that the company tanked
and the product disappeared.
But that's not where the story ends.
A decade later, I was at a C++ conference,
and I met one of the developers who used
to work at Sword back then.
I asked him what happened,
and he told me the story.
- Son, when we first started that project,
those yahoos in marketing
told us we had to be first
to market at all costs.
If we weren't first to
market, then there was
no point in even getting started.
So we rushed, son.
We rushed like a horse
in a raging brush fire.
Like a rabbit running
from a snarling wolf.
We rushed, and we made one hell of a mess.
When we were done, that
code looked like a whole
herd of hungry hogs had
stampeded through it.
I tell you, son, it was a
miracle that code worked at all.
And getting it working,
well, that was a bunch of
bailin', and hailin', and
hookin', and crookin',
and duct tape, and all
kinds of shenanigans,
but we got it working,
son, we got it working
just by the skin of our teeth.
Of course, then, it was all we could do
to keep it working, son,
'cause there was always
another bug fix or some
high priority feature.
The customers kept on wanting to write
bigger and bigger programs
and go faster and faster.
So we kept right on rushin',
son, there was no time
to go back and clean nothin'
up 'cause there was always
some new thing, some maximum
priority thingamawhats,
that some customer had to be satisfied.
We never managed to clean it, son.
And then, son, why, they
dropped a mother lode
of horse manure on the fan.
They told us we had just a few months
to get the whole thing workin' with C++.
C++, son, do you know how hard
it is to parse that language?
Well, it ain't easy, let me tell ya.
Now, we looked at that, we said,
"That was just impossible."
That code was already a
mess, it was more tangled
than a hay stack in a tornado.
Oh, we tried, son, we tried alright.
We worked on that like a mare giving birth
to a full-grown stallion.
We worked in the mornings,
we worked in the evenings,
we worked on the weekends.
We worked and we worked and we worked.
And we failed, son, we failed.
We couldn't make that tangled
mess of code parse C++.
It was a consign disaster, son.
And the reason we failed
was because we rushed in the first place.
- Okay, I admit it, I embellished
that a little bit, but
not actually by very much and
not in any substantive way.
What the guy told me was that
they rushed that C product
to market and made a
huge mess in doing it.
And then they couldn't transition to C++.
They saw their C market dwindling
away out from underneath
them, and they couldn't follow it into C++
because of the mess
they'd made in the code.
- It would appear that Sword Inc. was
destroyed by its own bad code.
At least in their case, the premise that
good code matters was not fragile at all.
- Yeah, okay, like, you know,
sure, but, but, like, why?
I mean what was it about the
bad code that killed them?
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
- Have you ever worked
on a greenfield project?
Do you remember how productive it was?
(keys clicking)
Do you remember how lightning
crackled from your finger tips
as you got feature after feature working.
- Yeah, (laughs) yeah, yeah.
I could just blast a whole
bunch of features together
in just a few hours. (laughing)
It was fun. (laughing)
- Yeah, man, like, you
know, they would come to me
and they'd ask me for a feature.
And I, I'd, like, have it ready
for 'em that same afternoon.
And so they really thought I was a hero.
- Yeah, I'm sure it felt like
you were going real fast,
but it didn't last, did it?
As the months went by, I'll
bet you started feeling
slower and slower until
you were barely crawling.
That's what happens to projects.
They start out fast, but then after a few
weeks or months, they slow way, way down.
And why?
Because there's a mess
building in the code.
The more that mess grows,
the harder it becomes
to add new features or
change existing code
until, finally, things that
would have taken you days
at the beginning now take
you weeks or even months.
But now think of it from
the manager's point of view.
They saw how fast you
were going at the start,
and they laid their plans
based on that speed.
They made promises to
customers based on that speed.
They don't understand why you slowed down.
All they understand is that
now they're looking at this
very scary gap, a gap that's
costing them a lot of money
and forcing them to
break a lot of promises.
What would you do if you
were one of those managers
and you saw your carefully
laid business plans
going up in smoke because the programmers
had inexplicably slowed down?
What would you do if you saw
the profit you expected turn
into a huge loss because the
programmers were going so slow?
- I would remind them of
the mission and suggest
that they find a more
intelligent way of working.
- Gosh, Uncle Bob, I
think I'd just kind of
sit them all down for some coffee or
maybe some herbal tea and ask
them what their issues were.
In the end, I think I'd probably end up
begging them to go faster. (laughing)
- Well, I'd tell those lazy
slackers to get moving.
I'd tighten their deadlines,
I'd mandate overtime.
And if any of them complained,
I'd show them the airlock.
- Of course none of that is
going to do a bit of good
because the problem is
not that the programmers
aren't working hard, they are.
The problem is that the
code is slowing them down,
so the harder they work,
the slower they'll go.
- And so, despite the
pressure, the threats,
the deadlines, and the
overtime, the productivity still
dwindles, and the scary
gap looms ever larger.
- [Professor] It seems to
me that the solution to this
problem is to hire more programmers.
After all, if you double the
staff, you double your speed.
- Well, not quite.
You see, there's this
thing called Brooks' law
which states that adding
manpower to a late project
makes it later.
It works like this.
The team is working along at
this level of productivity,
and then we decide to add more staff.
The productivity plummets
for a few weeks or months
as the new people suck the
life out of the old people,
but then the new people start to get smart
and their productivity rises.
In theory, it should rise
above where it was before.
- Except for one small logical flaw.
Precisely who is teaching the new people?
- The people who did this.
And it's not just the old
people teaching the new people,
it's the old code teaching the new people.
The more the new people
read through the old code
and deal with the old
code, the more they realize
how things are done around here.
And so they emulate the
behaviors that made the mess in
the first place, and, of course,
the mess continues to grow.
And so all hope of increasing
productivity is dashed
as the increasing mess
overwhelms the new staff
and the productivity resumes
its inexorable downward trend.
- Except now the business is spending
much more money on that new staff.
And so the scary gap has gotten
quite a bit scarier, hasn't it?
Hmph!
- Right.
Cash flow increases by a
step function when you add
new staff, and the decreasing
productivity makes that
scary gap that much scarier.
- (laughing) Yeah, maybe that was a fluke.
(laughing) Let's try it again.
(laughing)
- Indeed, lots of businesses
try this many times
because, after all, the
definition of sanity
is to repeat a failing
strategy until it succeeds.
But, of course, it doesn't succeed, and so
the scary gap continues to grow
and get scarier and scarier.
- At this point, it might be wisest
to consult with the
programmers themselves.
They are closest to the problem.
Perhaps they have a solution.
- Oh, yeah, sure they do. (laughs)
You want to guess what it is?
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
- (laughing) Yeah, start over.
(laughing) Throw it all away.
(laughing) Redesign the whole thing.
(laughing)
- Yeah, like, you know, the
best thing that could happen
to this system is for
someone to walk into the
machine room with a great big magnet.
- Oh, oh, Uncle Bob, I
want to be the architect.
Can I, can I please be the architect?
- As you might imagine, this
idea thrills the programmers
but terrifies the managers.
The managers know how much
money was spent on the
first design, and the thought
of spending all that money
all over again chills them to the marrow.
What's more, they've
got no confidence at all
that the redesign is actually
gonna solve the problem.
But here's the thing.
What other choice do the have?
I mean they've tried
everything else they know to do
and nothing worked, and they
can't go on the way things are.
So as scary as this option is,
it's kind of the last chance they've got.
And there's one other factor.
Programmers, you should never
underestimate your power
because you are the ones who know.
Managers don't, they
aren't the ones who know.
You know, you were hired because you know.
So if you beat the drums for a redesign,
as much as the managers might not like it,
you will eventually win
because the managers
understand that you're the ones who know.
- Well, yes, you'll win alright.
And it will be a disaster.
- And what a disaster it'll be.
But it doesn't start out
looking like a disaster, oh no.
On the day that the managers announce
that we're going to redesign the project,
a cheer goes up from the
development organization.
Hallelujah, we're going
back to the beginning.
We can be productive again.
We're gonna leave this mess behind.
We don't have to live in
the old code base anymore.
Of course, the next day in
the cold light of reality,
we realize that we are
not going to be the ones
who will be redesigning the system.
Management has picked the
10 best, the tiger team.
The ones who made the
mess in the first place.
They're gonna be the ones
who will sit in a room
working on a greenfield
project on the new design.
They're the ones who are gonna lead us
into a bright new future.
The rest of us hate those guys.
They're off doing some greenfield thing
while the rest of us are stuck
maintaining the old system
because, after all,
customers aren't gonna wait
months or years for new
features or bug fixes.
- And now just where do you think the
tiger team is going to get
their requirements from?
You don't actually believe there's an
accurate requirements document, do you?
- No, man, I mean
there's been way too many
late night fixes and midnight
modifications for that.
- (laughing) Yeah.
(laughing) The requirements
aren't in a document anymore.
(laughing) Now they're
buried in the old code.
(laughing)
- That's right.
The requirements are in the old code.
So that tiger team that's supposed to be
taking us into the future,
they're spending their time
poring over the old code,
trying to figure out just what it is
that the old system does.
And then they're trying to figure out
how they can reorganize
and repartition that code
so that it'll be better by
some definition of better.
Meanwhile, the rest of
us are working like dogs
to fix bugs and add new features.
So while the tiger team
is off studying the code,
we're busy changing it out from under 'em.
- The logical implication being
that the two factions are in a race.
- Right, a race.
And just like Achilles and the
tortoise in Zeno's paradox,
every time the tiger team got
to where the old system was,
we would've moved the old system
on with new features and new fixes.
- And while it is mathematically possible
to prove that Achilles will
eventually pass the tortoise,
that doesn't seem to work in software.
- I once worked for a company where that
race went on for 10 years.
10 years after we started the redesign,
development was still going on
and we were still shipping the old system.
Eventually, in desperation,
the managers decided
to replace all the old
systems in the field
with new systems even
though the new systems
couldn't do everything
the old systems could.
- I would imagine that the customers
were rather unhappy about that.
- Yeah, some of them
were pretty upset, but
that was nothing compared
to the developers.
You see, the tiger team
had long since gone on
to bigger and better things,
and the programmers that had replaced them
were racing like mad to
keep up with the old system.
They were horrified at the idea that
they'd actually deploy the new system.
They said, "You can't deploy this.
"It's crap, it's got to be redesigned."
The big redesign in the sky
is almost always a failing strategy.
Oh, it might work for a small thing
of a couple of man months or so,
but for big projects,
it's almost certain to end
in horrific waste and ultimate disaster.
So that's how bad code can destroy
a team, a division, and even a company.
- And so here's the bottom line.
You cannot deal with a mess
by running away from it.
The only way to effectively
deal with that mess
is to turn around and face it
and find the rot and clean it.
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
- What happens to software over time?
Why does it rot?
Why do the beautiful designs we start with
so often degrade and rot
into a festering pile?
- At the moment of
inception, the design of a
software system is usually a simple,
and elegant, and beautiful thing.
And likewise, when we
first write the code,
that code is simple, and
easy to change, and elegant,
and our hopes for the system are high.
- But with time, that code'll start to rot
like a piece of bad meat
sitting in a hot barn.
And the stink'll get so bad that not even
the hogs and crows will go near it.
- You can tell how old a piece of code is
by the facial expression of the developers
as they bring it up on their screens, hmm.
- Before we investigate why this happens,
let's study that stench in more detail.
What is it that makes
bad code smell so bad?
(mechanical sounds)
- Rigidity is the tendency
of a system to resist change.
- A system is rigid when
that system requires us
to make many changes to
many different places
in order to fix a single bug
or add a single new behavior.
Such a system resists change,
and so we say it is rigid.
- I'd really appreciate an example.
- Sure, let's now just say that your boss
comes to you one day and
shows you a bug report
and asks you if you can fix it.
You look at that bug
report and you realize
you know exactly where that bug is.
You know the line of code that bug is on
'cause you were just in that
module a week or two ago.
And you know how to fix it
too, it's gonna be easy.
It's gonna be easy-peasy,
simple as pie, no problemo.
So you give your boss the
minimum estimate: three weeks.
He goes away happy 'cause he got
the minimum estimate for that task.
Now you go to that module
and you scroll down
to where you think that bug is.
And sure enough, there it is
right like you thought it'd be.
So you reach right in
there and you fix it.
And you're about to go do something else
so you don't give your boss
the idea that your minimum
estimate was a little bit too long.
But then there's this itch
at the back of your head.
Something's bothering you
about that change, son.
And that's when you realize
that the change you just made to
that module is gonna break a
different module in the system.
So you plop back down and
bring that other module
up on your screen and scroll
to the place where you were
thinking about, and sure
enough you find a problem.
The change you made to the first module is
incompatible with the second.
So you reach into that
second module and you fix it.
And now you know what's coming, don't you?
Because sure as rain on a sunny day,
there's other modules in the
system that aren't sympatico
with the change you just
made to that second module.
So now you start going from
module to module to module
fixing issue after issue, trying to force
the system back into a consistent state.
You're like a dog chasing his
tail, burning lots of energy.
But you're not getting anywheres.
- And so the weeks will go by.
Two weeks, three weeks,
four weeks, six weeks,
and then your boss will come by
to find out what happened
to your three week estimate,
and you will undoubtedly
emit the pathetic phrase
that so many software developers
have said in the past,
"It was more complicated than I thought."
Hmph.
- Yeah, that's a rigid system.
And it shows one of the
most frustrating things
about rigid systems: their
wild unpredictability.
Estimating a fix or an
enhancement is fraught with error
because it's impossible to
properly determine the number
of modules that will actually be changed.
And so rigid systems blow estimates.
- (Laughing) Yeah.
(laughing) Boom!
(laughing)
(mechanical sounds)
- A fragile system is a
system that malfunctions
in many unpredictable ways when a
single simple change is made.
- We say that a system is fragile
when the repair of a single bug
or the addition of a single new feature
causes a malfunction in
one or many other parts
of the system that have no connection
with the part that was changed.
- I know, you want another
example, don't you?
Well, this here fella's got a good one.
- Long ago, I worked on a system
that tested telephone lines.
This system had 24 ASCII terminals
connected to a central mini computer.
The user interface was
character based and menu driven.
And the menus were hierarchical.
Deep down in one of the sub menus,
there was a grammatical error.
The word progress was spelled process.
We all knew about this error.
We all cringed whenever we saw it,
but there was never a
good reason to fix it.
Then one day, I was working in a module
and I happened to scroll past
the string for that menu.
It was an easy thing to
change, so I changed it.
I felt pretty good about that too.
Of course, I compiled it and I tested it.
I brought it up on the screen
to make sure that it fit
and there weren't any other
issues, and there weren't.
And so I added it to the list of changes
for the next release and I shipped it.
Hundreds of systems started
crashing in the field.
Not our systems, our customers' systems,
but they blamed us anyway.
We had customers on the telephone.
We had managers rampaging around,
pointing their fingers at people.
We had programmers
hiding under their desks.
What I had forgotten was that
in their infinite wisdom,
our marketing department
had told our customer
that the best way to interface
their systems to ours
was to plug their computers into
one of our RS232 terminal ports.
Of course, that meant that the customer's
software had to parse our menus.
So when I changed that menu,
it broke the customer's software.
My boss came to me and said,
"What the hell did you do?!"
And I said, I fixed a spelling error.
And he said, "Well, don't ever do that!"
- And so a fragile system
is a system that breaks
in unintended and unpredictable ways
when simple changes are made.
Such systems are terrifying
to managers and customers
because they are so wildly unpredictable.
- Indeed, when systems are fragile,
customers and managers
come to the conclusion
that the software developers
have lost control of their
software and don't know what
the hell they are doing.
Hmph!
(mechanical sounds)
- An inseparable system
is a system in which
those parts that might be
profitably used in another system
cannot be separated out
from the first system.
- Indeed, we say that
a system is inseparable
when the various points of that system
cannot be independent and be
used in some other system.
- Let me give you an example.
Let's say that I need a new car,
and I got very specific
requirements for this new car.
It's got to be silver,
it's got to seat six,
and it's got to go 200 miles an hour.
It turns out I talked to my
brother-in-law and he's got the car.
It's silver, it seats six,
it goes 200 miles an hour.
What's more, he just lost his license,
so he's gonna give it to me for free.
There's just one catch.
My brother-in-law's car has got a trailer.
(honking)
And this trailer ain't coupled
to the back of the car
with no hitch, no sir.
That trailer's welded
onto the back of that car.
The rear brakes have been
taken away from the car
and put on the back wheels of the trailer.
The rear lights have been put
on the back of the trailer.
The trailer is part of the car.
Now I gots me a really small
garage, and that trailer car,
well, it just ain't
gonna fit in that garage.
So I got to get rid of the
trailer off the back of that car.
I go take it to a mechanic.
I say, mechanic, take the
trailer off the back of this car.
(honking)
He looks at me like I'm crazy.
He says, "You can't take
the trailer off the back
"of this car, that
trailer's part of the car.
"It costs you lots more
than buying a new car.
"And what's more, I'm not
guaranteeing my work."
- To continue this example,
your boss comes to you one day
and says, "You know that
module you got to write?
"Well, there's this guy,
Joe, one floor below us
"who wrote a module just
like it about a year ago.
"You should go talk to
Joe and see how much
"of that module you can reuse."
Now, you know Joe, and you know
the kind of code Joe writes.
So you're not really anxious
to go wading through his code
to see if you can use any of it, but
your boss asked, so you have to do it.
So you get the code from
Joe and you look it over.
And sure enough, it does
exactly what you need.
But it's got a trailer.
Joe's code does a lot of
things you don't need.
And you realize that the
time and effort required
to decouple Joe's code so that you can
take the stuff you want and
leave behind the stuff you don't
is so large that you might as well
just write the module yourself.
So you go back to your boss
and you tell him that you
can't use Joe's code
because it's inseparable.
- Inseparable systems are unpredictable.
You never know if you
can reuse the components
in the system, and so the changes
cannot be reliably estimated, hmm.
(mechanical sounds)
- Opacity is the tendency of a system
to be so ineptly structured
that no amount of effort
can be applied to divine the
author's original intent.
- We say that a system is opaque
when reading the code
tells us little or nothing
about what the system
does or the way it works.
(pigs grunting)
- What they're trying to say
is that the code looks worse
than a pig sty in a rain storm.
- This picture really says it all.
Opaque code is hard to read,
hard to change, hard to understand.
- Meh!
(mechanical sounds)
- Raise your hands if you've ever been
significantly impeded by bad code.
(crowd clamoring)
And you guys out there on
the other side of the screen,
I see you out there, get
your hands up because
we've all been impeded by bad
code, significantly impeded.
The question is why did we write it?
- (laughing) Stupid managers.
(laughing)
- You know, like, man, we've
had some really impatient
customers and, well, I just couldn't wait.
- Oh, Uncle Bob, we just
have impossible schedules.
- Excuse me, but those are
just excuses and cop outs.
It's your fingers on the keyboard.
It's you that writes the code.
It's you, not them.
Hmm.
- Sherlock's right.
The only reason the code goes
bad is because we ruin it.
We're the ones who make the mess.
We rot the code.
- (laughing) Yeah.
But we got to go fast. (laughing)
And that's the only way
to go fast. (laughing)
- Yeah, like, I mean my
customers will never give me
the time to do things the right way.
- Yeah, Uncle Bob, we need to go fast, and
that's why we make the mess.
- I understand, you feel
the pressure of the deadline
and the urgency of the
customer, and so you rush.
But whenever you rush, you make a mess.
- Yeah, but, like, dude, you
know, we can always go back
and clean it later when
we're not in such a hurry.
- Go back and clean it later?
Go back and clean it later?!
Would you please tell me the last time
you went back and cleaned it later?!
- It doesn't happen, we all know that.
Deadline pressure doesn't
suddenly get less.
Customers don't suddenly get more patient.
Urgency never diminishes,
schedules never really relax.
We all know that saying that
we'll go back and fix it later
means we're never gonna go back at all.
The irony is that making messes
is not the way you go fast.
It's the way you go slow,
and you already know this.
You've acknowledged it, you said you were
significantly impeded by bad code.
- If you want to go fast,
you have to stay clean.
The only way to go fast is to go well.
- This can be hard to accept
because most of us feel
like we can get done faster by rushing.
The truth is, though, you can't.
If you rush through code,
you will always slow down.
Now some people think
that they can go faster
in the short term by rushing, even if that
slows them down in the long term,
but this is an illusion.
Rushing always slows you
down, even in the short term.
Making a mess is never
a strategy to go fast.
The only way to go fast in the short term
or the long term is to be clean.
- Ah, grasshopper.
Have you ever watched a
sushi chef prepare food?
The next time you go, pay close attention.
You can tell that the chef
has practiced his moves.
Every motion has a purpose.
Every motion is sure and quick.
Every motion is precise.
He cuts, he slices, he rolls, he positions
in a flurry of concentrated activity.
And then comes the magic moment
where he takes the dish and
he puts it in front of you.
The presentation is impeccable.
But, grasshopper, look at his workspace.
(gong hit)
His workspace is clean and spotless.
He has been cleaning
throughout the entire procedure
because, grasshopper, that is
the only way he can go fast.
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
- What is clean code?
I asked several experts that question.
And here's what they said.
Bjarne Stroustrup, the
inventor of C++, said,
"I like my code to be
elegant and efficient.
"Clean code should do one thing."
Elegant code is code that
does a lot in a few words.
Efficient code is code that
uses very few CPU cycles.
But what does it mean
for code to do one thing?
That's something we're gonna talk
about in an upcoming episode.
Grady Booch, the author
of this 1990s classic,
Object Oriented Design and
Analysis with Applications,
said, "Clean code is simple and direct.
"Clean code reads like
well-written prose."
We understand the simple and direct part,
that doesn't need a
lot of explanation, but
what does it mean for code to
read like well-written prose?
Is that even possible?
The simple answer to that
is, yes, it's possible.
The slightly longer answer
is, well, almost possible.
We'll actually have a
lot to say about this
in the next few episodes.
Michael Feathers, the author
of Working Effectively
with Legacy Code, said,
"Clean code always looks like
"it was written by someone who cares."
What a lovely remark.
We might be wonderful
if all the code we read
looked like it was written
by someone who cares.
Have you ever read code that looked
like the author didn't care at all?
This course is going to be about
learning how to care for our code.
Ward Cunningham, the inventor of wikis,
the inventor of more
things than I can mention,
the mentor of most of us, he said,
"You know you are reading clean code
"when every routine that you read
"is pretty much what you expected."
It's very much like Ward to
say something so profound
using words that sound so innocuous, but
think about it, when is the last time
you read code and thought to yourself,
"Yeah, this is pretty
much what I expected."?
Wouldn't it be nice if we
could all learn to write code
that was pretty much what
we expected, and, in fact,
that's what these videos are about:
how to write code that others will think
is pretty much what they expected.
(beeping sounds)
(keys clicking)
Robert Baden Powell, the
father of the boy scouts,
left a posthumous exhortation
to the organization he founded.
He told them, "Leave the world
better than you found it."
Now what if we did that with our code?
What if we left our code
better than we found it?
What if every time you
checked a module in,
you checked it in just a little
bit better than you checked it out?
What if you always did
some random act of kindness
to the code so that it
would be better and better,
and you never ever checked it in worse.
If we all did that, then
our code would simply get
better and better and better all the time,
and that, too, is what
this course is all about.
Well, that's it, that's our remake of
episode one, I hope you enjoyed it.
And if this is the first time
you've watched an episode,
well, you've got a lot to look forward to.
Episode two is all about
choosing good names.
Episode three, four,
and five are all about
functions and function structure.
Episode six is a two-parter
on test-driven development.
Episode seven is about architecture,
and then we start getting
into the solid principles,
and then the component principles,
and then advanced test-driven development.
And we have just scratched the surface.
There's a lot more coming.
(rock music)
The Scarier Gap, it's named
after a man named Fred Scarier.
Never mind, it's okay.
(laughing)
- [Camera Person] Alright, ready?
- No, I'm not ready at all, no.
Okay. (clears throat)
- [Camera Person] Action.
- Sure. (laughing)
Sure.
(laughing)
Let's now just say, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, alright, sure.
(clears throat) Yeah.
(laughing)
A rigid system. (fumbling words)
Estimating how long, yes, okay.
(droning sound)
(lip flapping sounds)
- Yeah, that's a rigid
system, alright, because,
you see, rigid systems are
wildly unpredictable, and
estimating them, trying to figure them out
is fraught with error and frustration
because, well, whatever.
Because, um, something.
'Cause you can never properly do.
- [Camera Person] Is fraught with error
because you can never properly determine,
all the parts of the
system are going to need
to be changed, so rigid
systems tend to blow estimates.
You were supposed to lip sync that.
- Well, I was trying.
- [Camera Person] It wasn't
very successful, I would say.
Let's do this, I feel good about
this next one.
- Yeah, yeah, do you?
- Mhmm.
- Okay, alright.
- [Camera Person] Action.
(laughing)
That's such a good one.
That's a good one.
- And so, rigid systems blow estimates.
- [Camera Person] Cut. Good job.
So if you looked right at me.
- 'Cause at the last minute I thought,
no, I'm talking about fragile systems.
- [Camera Person] Oh, you said 'em.
- Yeah, that's a rigid system,
and it shows one of the
most frustrating things
about rigid systems: their
wild unpredictability.
Estimating a fix or an
enhancement is fraught with error
because it's impossible
to properly determine
the number of modules that
will actually be changed.
And so, rigid systems blow estimates.
- Cut.
- Yeah!
(laughing)
- Cannot be predicted, blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
Blah, blah, blah.
- Mmm, saltamontes,
has visto alguna vez a
un chef de Sushi preparar comida?
Ayuda, ayuda!
(Risas)